John Owed III

419-450-7894 • johnowed@gmail.com • Seattle, WA • www.linkedin.com/in/johnowed

SUMMARY

12+ years of analytics and data science experience and 6+ years of leading teams. I deliver large scale data projects and coach data professionals to perform at their best. My focus is on driving business outcomes. When not working with my team members and stakeholders, I love finding patterns and trends in data through coding in SQL (expert) and R/Python (intermediate).

SKILLS & TECHNOLOGY

Technologies: SQL, SAS, Redshift, S3, Python, R, ETL, Hadoop, S3, SparkSQL, Quicksight, Power BI, Tableau

Skills: Clustering (K-means, hierarchical), Regression, AN(C)OVA, A/B Testing, Experimental design, ML applications, Personalization

Certifications: SAS Base 9 Programmer, AWS Cloud Practitioner, Machine Learning, Data Science in Python, R Programming

WORK EXPERIENCE

Amazon • Seattle, Washington

Jan 2018 - Present

Manager, BI, Analytics & Data Science, Amazon Grocery Instore & Ads

Nov 2021 - Present

- First data team member with zero people, processes or infrastructure in place, built data infrastructure utilizing Redshift (AWS), Hadoop (SparkSQL), S3, and ETL (SQL) for reporting, ad-hoc analysis and analytics/data science (R/Python/SageMaker)
- Hiring and on-boarding business intelligence engineers (BIEs), upskilling and training to deliver on projects within first two weeks; currently growing data science capability with the hiring of two data scientists
- Define requirements for data gathering initiatives with product (PMs) and tech (SDEs/SDMs) to implement new metrics within Amazon's data lake and build out daily/weekly reporting to inform business teams of product performance (SQL/Excel/Tableau)
- · Creating measurement and experimentation frameworks (SQL/R) for in-store testing of newly launched Ad products

Manager, BI, Analytics & Data Science, Reading Subscriptions

Oct 2019 - Oct 2021

- Built, managed and led a multi-disciplinary team consisting of four BIEs, a data engineer and two applied/data scientists (8HC charter, grown from previous Sr. Analytics Lead IC role)
- Delivered self-serve BI solutions to product managers and tech teams such as flash reports, dashboards and ad-hoc analysis
- Scaled and improved multiple types of models (boosted trees/regression/time series) to value content for our reading subscription programs, reducing MAPE by 30% on average
- Created innovative approaches for applying ML to attract new subscribers and retain members with personalization (built with Python/Scala), leading to an incremental \$70MM Annualized LTV
- Evaluated performance of personalization models (Transformer/Similarity) utilizing Accuracy, Precision & Recall metrics

Sr. Analytics Lead, Kindle Unlimited and Prime Reading

Jan 2018 - Sep 2019

- Created end-to-end data products utilizing the full spectrum of analytics tools (Hadoop/SQL/Excel/Quicksight/Tableau)
- Worked with product managers and tech leads to perform ad-hoc and in-depth analysis to determine drivers of growth for our reading subscription member base, resulting in new revenue streams and business models (such as bundled promotions)
- Launched the first Books org customer engagement and purchase segmentation, uncovering new ways to increase purchasing
- Built project prioritization and analytics support models that were adopted by five other analytics teams within the Books org

Data Republic • Head of Data Products • Sydney, Australia

Oct 2015 - Dec 2017

- Grew a team of data scientists and analytics professionals to build products on our data sharing platform (5 HC)
- Developed and delivered the company's highest revenue product for an out-of-home advertising company consisting of 4+ billion data points extrapolated to the Australian population with geographic map visualizations (SQL/R/Tableau)
- Drove platform engagement and self-serve through facilitating workshops, trainings and developing SQL code libraries

Quantium • Team Lead, Grocery Retail Analytics • Sydney, Australia

Jan 2014 - May 2015

- Led a team of analysts mining customer insights and delivering recommendations to grocery client Woolworths (4 HC)
- Utilized hierarchical clustering models (R) and association metrics (Yule's Q) to analyze grocery product affinities and used these to recommend optimized store layouts to Woolworth's 1000+ grocery stores
- Built personalization algorithms (SAS) for direct mail and email campaigns for millions of customers across Australia

dunnhumby • Senior/Data Analyst • Cincinnati, Ohio • Sacramento, California

Jun 2009 - Dec 2013

- Performed exploratory data analysis (EDA), ANCOVA and regression on Kroger's 60+ million customer database to deliver projects to CPG clients such as PepsiCo, Mondelēz and Kraft
- Built targeting algorithms (RFM/regression) for personalized direct mail and email campaigns utilizing A/B Testing
- Worked with international teams to automate solutions and reduce analyst workload (resulting in ~1.5 FTEs saved annually)

EDUCATION

Xavier University • Masters of Business Administration • Cincinnati, Ohio

Jan 2011 - Dec 2013

Relevant Coursework: Business Leadership, Small Business Consulting, Marketing Analytics

Miami University ● B.S. Mathematics and Statistics ● Cum Laude ● Oxford, Ohio

Aug 2005 - May 2009

Relevant Coursework: Experimental Design, Linear Algebra, Probability Theory, Computer Programming (VBA)

INTERESTS/HOBBIES